<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Dental Care</string>
    <string name="about"> \nOur office has become our patient’s dental “home”.
       \n Our patients are made to feel welcome and comfortable with each visit.
        \nOur comprehensive care philosophy is to maintain and provide our dental family with the finest and most personalized dental care available.
        \nWe are dedicated to providing top quality service and satisfaction at all times.
        \nOur success is measured by our patient’s willingness to recommend our dental care to their friends and family.
    \nOur services cover the full range of family dental services, from pediatric dental care to root canals, implants, crowns, bridges, all types of fillings, tooth whitening and Invisalign, to mention a few.  We also provide sedation dentistry for those who desire it.
\n
Our extended hours are provided to accommodate the schedules of shift workers and students, as well as professionals in the private service field.
\n
It’s our hope that you will find the dental procedures and oral care methods discussed on our website, helpful and enlightening.
\n
We have several locations in Hamilton to serve our dental ‘family’. Please feel free to give us a call if you have questions or would like to schedule an appointment.

    </string>

    <string name="philosophy">Our first and most important concern is you and your smile. Our motto goes this way: “We will give you something to smile about”. That is why we have put together a group of professionals, using state-of-the art equipment to make your visit feel like you have a wining team on your side. Grover Dental Care is ‘home’ to our patients and we welcome you</string>


    <string name="standards">are based on the “best practices” available in dentistry today. That gives us the edge we need, to provide the care you deserve. Treatment planning for every aspect of your dental program is a joint effort, between you and our dental team. From your first visit through every stage of your dental care, our ultimate goal is to see that you enjoy optimal oral health.</string>
    <string name="safety">is uncompromising. We maintain strict sterilization and contamination processes to protect our family of patients. We use standards that are recommended by the Royal College of Dental Surgeons (RCDSO), the Center for Disease Control (CDC) and the Occupational Safety and Health Administration (OSHA).</string>

    <string name="wisdom">Commonly known as third molars; wisdom teeth are the last teeth to emerge and tend to come through between the ages of 17 and 25. For some people they erupt without any problems – the same as all other teeth, but for others they can create a range of oral and general health concerns which in turn need often be extracted.</string>
<string name="gum_disease">Early prevention is advantageous as advanced bone loss resulting from periodontal disease is usually irreversible; your gums and jawbone are the foundations for your teeth.
\n
Correct oral hygiene should be taught in the home from a young age, this includes proper brushing and flossing techniques, having a healthy diet and attending regular dental check-ups to ensure that your teeth last a lifetime.
\n
Following a simple daily oral hygiene routine of brushing at least twice a day and flossing once a day will significantly improve your dental and overall health.
\n
The effectiveness of this routine is important so that you can avoid extensive dental treatments in the future.</string>

    <string name="knocked">If the knocked out tooth is dirty, hold it by the crown (not roots) and rinse it in milk. If milk is not available then use water but only for a few seconds or have patient suck it clean, then put the tooth back in the socket. If the tooth cannot be replanted, wrap in Glad Wrap or place it in milk or in the patient’s mouth inside the cheek. It is essential to see us within 30 minutes if you can as timing is critical for successful replanting.</string>
<string name="xrays">Various forms of x-rays enable your Coral Dental dentist to obtain important information, which is then used in planning your treatment. They show the condition of your teeth, roots, jaw placement and the overall composition of your facial structure.

They are invaluable for diagnosing the presence of gum disease, abscesses and any abnormal growths, including cysts and tumours. They are vital in the early detection of cavities and assist in determining other signs of disease not able to be seen during a visual exam.

 </string>

    <string name="brush">The accumulation of food particles on your tongue and between your teeth not removed during your daily oral cleaning, react with bacteria and cause bad breath. Some people battle with constant bad breath, using mints, mouthwash and gum, which only mask the problem and not cure it.

Adopting an effective at home oral hygiene routine and scheduling professional cleaning appointments to remove plaque and tartar build-up every six – twelve months, depending on your current state of oral health, can restore your mouth to full health and make your breath fresh.

In some cases, persistent bad breath can indicate you have a more serious health problem, including a gastrointestinal, respiratory or sinus problem. In this instance we advise that you consult with your GP.</string>

    
 <string name="headache">A headache can be an inconvenience easily relieved with an everyday headache tablet and often there is little thought as to its cause, with many people putting it down to strained neck or shoulder muscles from a bad night’s sleep or a sport strain. For some people this may be true, but very few would think their teeth and jaw might be the cause of their headache.

So when something goes wrong with your jaw joints, it can cause you much discomfort. With the right diagnosis and treatment by Coral Dental’s dedicated team, most people find relief from the pain and other symptoms of a TMJ disorder.

 </string>

    <string name="diabetes">Recent studies have also indicated a correlation between gum disease and an increased risk of stroke, heart attack and type II diabetes. It is believed this is due to the toxins from gum disease entering the bloodstream and adhering to the sticky plaque and fatty deposits on artery walls, constricting or preventing blood flow.
\n
This is due to the bacterium from gum disease entering the bloodstream through microscopic cuts in the gums made from brushing and flossing too vigorously, this bacterium then adheres to plaque in the artery walls restricting blood flow, contributing to a heart attack or stroke.</string>

    <string name="ftime">
        \nAt AKVS Dental, we want your children to have the best dental health possible. Visits to a dentist by children as young as 2 years of age, is important in order to detect any problems in growth and oral health as soon as possible. Early visits also gets them used to having their teeth checked, relieving any problems of visits as they get older.</string>



  <string name="desc1">Everybody has undoubtedly heard the popular saying,  Prevention is better than cure.  This phrase is applicable more than ever in dentistry because the longer dental problems go unaddressed, the treatments can become exponentially expensive — and painful. Many people put off seeing a dentist until an oral health problem becomes too agonizing to ignore, necessitating extensive and costly treatments. Luckily for you, modern dentistry has many solutions to make sure that today s minor irritation does not turn into tomorrow s major agony.
\n
Preventive dentistry can help arrest tooth decay or other diseases in the earlier stages. The goal is to keep your teeth as healthy as possible and maintain your natural teeth for life.
\n
Visiting AKVS Dental Clinic every six months for a check-up and cleaning can help prevent these problems from occurring in the first place. If you develop an issue with your teeth or gums, regular checkups ensure that our team can treat and also, in some cases, reverse your problems with conservative measures. The time and efforts you put into maintaining your oral health is an investment that will reap great rewards for your future health.
\n\n
Preventive Dentistry Procedures:
\n
AKVS Dental Clinic offers you these common dental treatments which are carried out as a form of oral preventive procedures. In other words, these procedures are designed to form part of your personal dental hygiene plan which aims to keep your teeth clean and healthy. These include:
\n
Scaling and Polishing: Scaling and Polishing are also known as dental cleaning. Dental cleanings involve removing disease-causing plaque and tartar (calculus) deposits that have built up on your teeth over time – especially in areas near the gum line that are hard to reach. Regular and professional scaling and polishing are vital to the health of your teeth.
\n
Pit and Fissure Sealants: Tooth decay occurs much faster in children than in adults. Sealants should be applied to a child’s teeth as soon as possible, before decay has had a chance to set in. These invisible plastic coatings fill the tiny grooves in the back teeth, so they do not become a breeding haven for bacteria. Decay will not start under a fissure sealant because the decay-causing organisms are deprived of the food and oxygen they need to flourish. The use of sealants substantially reduces the risk of tooth decay by keeping food and bacteria out of cavity prone areas.
\n
Fluoride Treatment: Treatment regimens with fluoride are developed for the prevention of dental caries. Your dentist can directly incorporate fluoride into your teeth s mineral structure, thereby making them decay-resistant and stronger. It can also reverse tiny cavities that are starting to form on your teeth. Fluoride is good for strengthening the teeth as well as providing essential minerals to any teeth that have been eroded by acid.
\n
Orthodontic Expansion: Growth or expansion appliances are used by nearly all dentists or orthodontists as they are often a better alternative to teeth extraction. The ideal time for expansion is while the maxillary canines are erupting. If we perform this procedure too early, it would most probably need to be repeated after these teeth erupt. Expansion is often a better alternative to teeth extraction.
\n\n
Your Role in Preventing Dental Disease:
The procedures mentioned above can only help you if you visit AKVS Dental Clinic to take advantage of them. By regular visits to our clinic, you can ensure healthy oral care, preventing problems from arising in the first place. However, effective prevention begins at home and we cannot stress enough the importance of maintaining a good oral hygiene routine for you and your family. Even after your regular visits to our clinic, daily flossing and brushing your teeth will go a long way towards keeping dental diseases away.
</string>

    <string name="desc2">At AKVS Dental Centre, Dr. Tarun Giroti, who firmly advocates holistic dentistry, wholeheartedly believes that it is far better to save and treat a tooth where possible than to remove it. Thanks to endodontic treatments, extracting a tooth is no longer your only option.
 Root Canal Therapy  is the more common name of Endodontics. Root canal therapy is the treatment of infection or disease found inside the tooth. It is used to salvage seriously infected teeth which would otherwise have required extracting.

\n\nSome symptoms which may highlight the need for root canal treatment include:

 \nSerious levels of tooth decay or an injury that causes an abscess or infection in the bone.
 \nThe development of sensitivity when hot or cold drinks or food is consumed.
 \nSpontaneous pain or throbbing during biting.
\n
If you are experiencing any of the above issues, we strongly recommend you schedule a consultation with our friendly team today. If your tooth does require an extraction, we may be able to treat it using endodontics and save your valuable tooth!</string>

 <string name="desc3">Early Orthodontics Could Mean Less Treatment Later
\n
It s never too late, or too early to think about braces. It could be a child starting school or a young adult graduating from college or a mature adult. If you observe old school pictures from the 1970s or  80s, it would be common to see many smiles which are framed with heavy metal braces. It s a sight that s much less common in high schools today. That’s because children these days tend to get braces at a much earlier age. There are some patients with special problems who begin orthodontic treatment at age 7 or younger.
\n\n
When is the best time to begin treatment?
\n
Orthodontic treatment can be started on certain types of tooth problems before all permanent teeth have erupted. Early treatment usually begins after the four permanent upper and lower front teeth have erupted (age 7-9) and recommended when any of the problems illustrated on this page are apparent.
\n\n
The advantages of early treatment include:

\n Moving the front teeth back so they will be less susceptible to injury.
 \nImproving the relationship to upper and lower jaws, allowing more normal future growth and development.
 \nUsing maximum advantage of growth for successful treatment.
 \nImproving facial appearance and self-esteem
\n
Adolescent and Adult treatment
\n
Today, more than 30% of orthodontic patients are over 18 years old. Crooked teeth, improper bite, overcrowding and ‘Buck teeth’ are now being corrected in many people, regardless of age. The major difference between the orthodontic treatment for adults and children is that adult bones are no longer growing. This means that it may take a little longer for adult teeth to move into their correct position. In general, adult treatment takes between 12 and 21 months.
\n
Adolescent and adults have more choices than ever before to be able to correct their smiles. From traditional braces to "clear" braces, the number of effective and cosmetically pleasing treatment option is growing all the time.
\n\n
Treatment Timing and Phases
\n
Orthodontic treatment can be completed in one full length treatment or broken into two separate treatment phases with a maintenance phase between the two. Please keep in mind that treatment times depend on several factors.
\n
 Aesthetic Braces: Aesthetic Braces give you a lot of smile about. When you’re wearing Aesthetic Braces, your natural beauty shines through every time you smile.

     \n
Smooth, sculptured and translucent, Aesthetic Braces are the ultimate fashion accessory in orthodontic wear.
Aesthetic braces won’t stain or discolour and will look at good the day they come off as the day your orthodontist put them on.
SmartClip Self Ligating Braces: SmartClip Braces are the modern choice in orthodontics. They are computer designed and use a special nickel-titanium metal alloy to make your treatment more comfortable, save time and give you the result you want – a beautiful new smile.
\n
SmartClip braces are different. They don’t use ligatures to hold the archwire... They re self-ligating. Instead of elastic bands, SmartClip braces use small metal clips to hold the archwire into the bracket. So you can forget about the problems associated with elastic bands.
\n
Invisalign
\n
Choose the nearly invisible way to straighten your teeth.
\n
Very few people have naturally straight teeth. And for years, braces were the only option until now. Introducing Invisalign, a revolutionary new way to straighten teeth without braces – so invisible, you’ll be the only one that knows.
\n
Invisalign uses a series of nearly undetectable aligners instead of brackets and wires. So, if it’s really hard for people to tell you’re wearing Invisalign even up close. Invisalign can give you the smile you’ve always wanted without the braces you’ve always avoided.
\n
Retention
\n
As soon as your treatment is complete and your braces are removed, you will be given retainers. Proper use of your retainer is essential to establish a stable tooth relationship and keep your smile looking beautiful. Retainers should always be worn as directed by Dr. Bhagat.
\n
An Investment in your future
\n
You can be sure we’ll do everything possible to guarantee that your orthodontic investment is a wise choice for many years to come. The orthodontic brackets you’ll be wearing are made from quality materials polished to a smooth rounded surface with the smallest dimensions possible. The brackets are less noticeable, more hygienic and far more attractive than they were in the past.
\n
We think it’s important for you to know that the brackets you’ll be wearing are new. Our orthodontics practice does not use reconditioned brackets. We assure you of the best treatment in the shortest period of time. During the testament, it will be especially important to follow all of our instructions. Good oral hygiene is of utmost importance during orthodontic treatment. We’ll tell you the best way to keep your teeth clean and your brackets sparking.
\n
You can be sure that our orthodontic treatment will be an investment that will benefit you for a lifetime.


 </string>



<string name="desc4">Prosthodontists are dentists who specialize in the aesthetic restoration and replacement of teeth. They can help restore optimum function and appearance to your smile.

\nAt AKVS Dental Clinic, we help you get back your healthy, beautiful smile. Our team offers a full spectrum of cosmetic and restorative dental services including crowns, dental implants, porcelain veneers, teeth whitening and more. Whether treatment requires delicate enhancement by bonding, whitening and straightening or demands more complex procedures, we have the perfect tools to provide you with the personalized care that you deserve.
\n
Dental Crowns
\n
Restore your Teeth with Dental Crowns:
\n
Our specialists can repair infected, damaged or chipped teeth with dental crowns. You may benefit from a dental crown if a tooth is:
\n Broken or cracked
\n Severely discoloured
 \nDecayed
    \n\n
DWhat Are Dental Crowns?

Dental crowns are ‘caps’ that cover your natural tooth made to fit snugly at the gum line to protect the remainder of your tooth. Not only can crowns cover decay or cracks, they can work together with dental bridges to help hold a replacement tooth and cover dental implants.
\n\n
What Are Crowns Made Of?

We use crowns made from porcelain and can match a crown to the exact color of the surrounding teeth. The benefit of a porcelain crown allows for a more natural looking solution for functional and aesthetic tooth problems. Your restoration will be virtually unnoticeable.
\n\n
Why Visit AKVS Dental Clinic?\n

There are many cases in which you should visit a prosthodontist. Some of them are:
 \nYou need dental implants
 \nYou have one or more teeth missing
 \nYou wear dentures or partial dentures
 \nYou have worn or damaged teeth
 \nYou need to improve your smile aesthetically
\nOur prosthodontists are highly trained in state-of-the-art procedures and techniques for treating various dental conditions and restoring smiles. These include: Bridges, crowns, veneers, removable and complete partial dentures, traumatic injuries to the mouth’s structure and/or teeth, dental implants, and sleep or snoring disorders.

\nIf you are interested in Prosthodontics or would like to schedule an appointment, please don’t hesitate to contact us. One of our friendly team members will be always happy to assist you.

\nWhen you trust your mouth and teeth to our Prosthodontists, you can be rest assured that you will receive the best quality care from true professionals with the necessary experience and training to provide your treatment.</string>
    <string name="desc5">Periodontal literally means  around the tooth . Periodontal disease attacks the bones that support the teeth as well as the gums. Plaque is a sticky film of food debris, bacteria, and saliva. If plaque is not removed, it turns into calculus (tartar). When plaque and calculus are not removed, they start destroying the gums and bone. Periodontal disease is characterized by red, swollen, and bleeding gums.

A number of people suffering from periodontal disease are not even aware of it! This is because the disease is usually painless in the early stages.

Dental curettage is a procedure in which diseased tissue is removed from the gums and mouth. Gum curettage is a common technique used to manage periodontal disease. In basic dental curettage, a sharp cutting instrument is run into gingival pockets in front of the teeth to remove dead tissue, and dead or infected tissue will be removed from the gums. A local anaesthetic is often used to make the patient more comfortable, and the mouth is frequently flushed with a sterile solution to sweep out the debris. This procedure is usually provided to people with advanced gum disease as a tool for managing the problem, and it may be required on multiple occasions.

Not only is periodontal disease the number one reason for tooth loss, research suggests that there could be a link between periodontal disease and other diseases such as, stroke, bacterial pneumonia, diabetes, cardiovascular disease, and increased risk during pregnancy. Researchers are determining if inflammation and bacteria associated with periodontal disease affect these systemic diseases and conditions. Smoking also increases the risk of periodontal disease.

Good oral hygiene, a balanced diet, and regular visits to the dentist can help reduce your risk of developing periodontal disease.
\n\n
Signs and symptoms of periodontal disease:
\n Bleeding gums – Ideally gums should never bleed, even when you brush vigorously or use dental floss
 \nLoose teeth – This could be caused by bone loss
\nNew spacing between teeth – Caused by bone loss
 \nPersistent bad breath – Caused by bacteria in the mouth
 \nPus around the teeth and gums – Sign that there is an infection present
 \nReceding gums – Loss of gum around a tooth
 \nRed and puffy gums – Gums should never be red or swollen
 \nTenderness or Discomfort – Plaque, calculus, and bacteria irritate the gums and teeth
\nIn preference to curettage, some dentists prefer to do perform what is known as a  deep cleaning , otherwise known as a scaling and root planing.

\nStudies have suggested that deep scaling and root planing may be just as effective, especially when it is done at an early stage. In this procedure, built-up calculus is removed from the teeth with hand-held instruments, and the roots of the teeth are smoothed so that they do not provide a surface for plaque to build up on. Several sessions are often required, and patients may be given anaesthetic so that they feel more comfortable, since the procedure can be mildly painful.

At AKVS Dental Clinic, we are committed to the highest level of periodontal excellence. Our team is friendly, courteous, and always ready to assist you in any way.</string>


<string name="desc6">\nAt AKVS Dental Clinic, we understand that a dental clinic visit can be a daunting aspect for nervous patients. It is very common for patients to have concerns and worries about visiting their dentist. For some people, their fears about getting dental procedures done become a phobia that can prevent them from getting the treatment and care they need.

\nThe team at AKVS has a lot of experience with nervous patients. They can help you with your dental phobia by talking through your worries and explaining every aspect of your treatment. In our experience, knowledge is power. The dentist will tell you about every stage of the procedure you will undergo so that it is easy for you to understand exactly what is happening at all times. Noises, equipment and materials will be explained in advance, so you know what to expect, when and why. Hopefully, with patience and time, we can help you rationalise your fears and make you feel relaxed and calm whenever you visit us.

\nYou can feel free to bring someone along with you to the clinic for moral support during your treatment.

\nWe offer sedation dentistry treatments in the form of Inhalation Sedation and General Anesthesia to ensure that you never skip your next dental appointment again. Here is how they work:

\nInhalation Sedation: At AKVS Dental Clinic, Nitrous Oxide (N2O) is given as inhalation through a nasal mask. N2O is simply a sweet-smelling, colourless, non-irritating gas which you can breathe in. It has been the primary means of sedation in dentistry for many years. Nitrous oxide can produce a fast-acting, safe and relaxed euphoria that will start before your treatment and will last while you are getting treated.

\nGeneral Anesthesia: An anti-anxiety medication is injected into the bloodstream through a vein by an anesthetist to induce a state of deep relaxation. Most of you will have absolutely no recollection of the treatment afterwards, which makes it perfect for anxious or nervous patients.

\nBoth these methods are ideal for overcoming your fears or making lengthier procedures in the chair more comfortable. They are mainly administered so that patients can receive dental services without knowing or feeling a thing.

\nOverall, you can speak to Dr. Giroti about any concerns you may have about our sedation techniques, and we can work together to ensure you have a great dental experience!</string>

<string name="desc7">Holistic dentistry, also known as biological dentistry, takes into account a patient s dental health considering their entire state of physical and emotional health. At AKVS Dental Clinic, we strive to use natural therapies (often in combination with conventional ones) to diagnose, prevent and treat diseases of the oral cavity.

\nIt is estimated that 80% of the chronic degenerative disease originates in the mouth.
According to reports, dental amalgam fillings are the primary source of mercury exposure for the general population. In fact, mercury has been known to stay in the body for up to a year.

\nDentists practicing holistically look at the complete wellbeing of the patient, not just the gums and teeth. At AKVS Dental Clinic, we do not use amalgam, nickel, or other metals to fill cavities. Instead, we use composite resin which is a much healthier material.

\nWe take the utmost care while restoring teeth. There are several choices of non-toxic dental materials available. Composites (also known as bonding), porcelain and gold are all available. In Dr. Tarun s years of experience, he has narrowed his material choices to specific holistic materials. Thus, there are no known traces of either metals or other elements that might affect the patient s health. Dr. Tarun also takes the time to explain the patient s condition and give options (i.e. fillings verses inlays/onlays) to suit their finances and wants.

\nHolistic and integrative approaches are important in any area of medicine, and Dr. Tarun believes that dentistry is no exception. The patient can feel free to ask him questions such as the types of materials used in his clinic for dental procedures, whether they use digital X-rays, and how they dispose of medical waste. He also does not necessarily agree or conform to all traditional practices among holistic dentists. In particular, he believes that removing existing amalgam fillings is pointless, expensive and stressful to the patient. He advocates evaluating fillings and exchanging the amalgam for composite resin only when they break down and need to be redone.

\nAt AKVS, the patient s well being is our priority.</string>


   <string name="post">Oral surgical wounds usually heal quickly and without complication if simple precautions are taken. Sometimes the after-effects of oral surgery are quite minimal, so not all of the following instructions may apply. Common sense will often dictate what you should do. However, when in doubt, follow these guidelines or call our office for clarification.
\n\nDay Of Surgery\n
\nTHE FIRST FEW HOURS: Bite down gently but firmly on the gauze packs that have been placed over the surgical areas, making sure they remain in place. Do not change them for the first hour or two unless the bleeding is not controlled. The packs may be gently removed after one hour (the greater the surgical procedure, the longer the packs should remain in place). If active bleeding persists, place enough new gauze to obtain pressure over the surgical site for another 30–60 minutes. The gauze may then be changed as necessary (typically every 30–45 minutes). It is best to moisten the gauze with tap water and loosely fluff it for more comfortable positioning.
\n\nWOUND CARE: A good blood clot will help healing, so do not disturb the surgical area today, and do not rinse vigorously or probe the area with any objects. You may brush your teeth gently, avoiding the surgical area. Avoid vigorous exercise for the first several days. If you smoke, please do not smoke for at least 48 hours, since this is detrimental to healing and may cause a dry socket. Avoid alcohol for the next several days.
\n\nOOZING: Intermittent bleeding or oozing overnight is normal. This may be controlled by placing fresh gauze over the areas and biting on the gauze for 30–45 minutes at a time.
\n\nPERSISTENT BLEEDING: Bleeding should never be severe. If so, it usually means that the packs are being clenched between the teeth only and they are not exerting pressure on the surgical areas. Try repositioning the gauze packs. If bleeding persists or becomes heavy, you may substitute a tea bag (soaked in very hot water, squeezed damp/dry and wrapped in a moist gauze) for 20–30 minutes. If bleeding remains uncontrolled, please call our office.
\n\nSWELLING: Oral surgery is often associated with post-operative swelling. It can be minimized by using a cold pack, ice bag, or a bag of frozen peas wrapped in a towel and applied firmly to the cheek — twenty minutes on, twenty minutes off — during the first 24 hours after surgery. It is especially important to do this for the first few hours after surgery. In your instruction bag, you are provided a surgical glove which can be filled with ice and used as an ice pack if needed. If you have been prescribed medicine for the control of swelling, be sure to take it as directed. Immediate and constant gauze compression on the wound and between the gum and cheek, firm, gentle pressure on the cheek with an ice pack, and elevation of the head are the best ways to minimize swelling.
\n\nPAIN: Unfortunately, most oral surgery is accompanied by some degree of discomfort, depending on the procedure and patient. You will usually have a prescription for pain medication. If you take the first pill before the anesthetic has worn off, you should be able to manage the discomfort better. The effects of pain medication vary widely among individuals. If you do not achieve adequate relief at first, you may supplement each pain pill with an analgesic such as ibuprofen. Rarely, some patients may initially even require two pain pills at one time. It is best to limit as much as possible the use of pain medication, as overuse can lead to negative side effects, without any added beneficial effects.
Remember that the most severe pain is usually within 6 hours after the local anesthetic wears off; after that, your need for pain medication should lessen with time. If you find yourself needing to take large amounts of pain medicine at frequent intervals, please call our office. Also, do not drive while taking this medication.
\n\nDIET: Eat any nourishing food that can be taken with comfort. Avoid extremely hot or cold foods. Do not use a straw for the first few days after surgery. It is usually advisable to confine the first day’s intake to liquids or pureed foods (soups, pudding, yogurt, milk, fruit shakes, etc.). Avoid hard foods, which may be lodged in the socket areas. Over the next several days, you may gradually progress to solid foods. If you are diabetic, maintain your normal eating habits or follow instructions given by your doctor.
\n\nSHARP EDGES: If you feel something hard or a sharp edge in the surgical areas, it is likely you are feeling the bony walls which once supported the extracted teeth. Occasionally small slivers of bone may work themselves out during the following week or so. If they cause concern or discomfort, please call our office.
</string>

    <string name="post1">\n\nMOUTH RINSES: Keeping your mouth clean after surgery is essential. Use ¼ teaspoon of salt dissolved in an 8-ounce glass of warm water and gently rinse portions of this solution, taking 5 minutes to use the entire glassful. Repeat as often as you like, but at least 2 or 3 times daily, preferably after meals, for 1 week after surgery. Avoid commercial mouth rinses, as they contain a small amount of alcohol in them.
\n\nBRUSHING: Begin your normal oral hygiene routine as soon as possible after surgery, normally the day after surgery. Soreness and swelling may not permit vigorous brushing, but please make every effort to clean your teeth within the bounds of comfort.
\n\nHEALING: Normal healing after tooth extractions should be as follows: The first two days after surgery are generally the most uncomfortable and there is usually some swelling and/or bruising in the affected area. On the third day, you should be more comfortable and, although still swollen, can usually begin a more substantial diet.
The remainder of the post-operative course should be a gradual, steady improvement. If you don’t see continued improvement, please call our office.
\n\nDRY SOCKET: This is an occasional complication after tooth extraction, especially with third molars (wisdom teeth) and lower teeth. It is caused by the blood clot dissolving too early, and it is identified by increased pain/discomfort after the first few days of normal healing. While this process is self-limiting, it can be uncomfortable. Please call our office as soon as possible so we can treat you and relieve your pain.
\nCommon temporary post-operative symptoms:
\nJaw stiffness with difficulty in opening
\nA slight earache on the side of the surgery
\nYour other teeth may ache. This is “sympathetic” pain.
\nThe corners of your mouth may be dried, cracked, or bruised. Use cream or ointment to keep the area moist and to promote healing.
\nBlack and blue discolorations or bruising may occur on the face in the area of surgery. This should resolve itself within several days.
\nThere may be an elevation of body temperature for 24–48 hours (up to 101° F). If temperature persists, please call our office.
\nRemember, you just had a surgical operation. Be kind to yourself.
\nIt is our desire that your recovery is as smooth and pleasant as possible. Following these simple instructions will assist you in your recovery, but if you have any questions about your progress, please call our office at (484) 231-1177.
</string>

</resources>

